<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short relation of the most remarkable transactions in several parts of Europe between the Christians and Turks including an exact diary of the siege of Buda / written originally by a person of honour, a voluntier in the compagne, and done into English by P.R.</title>
            <author>Person of honour, a voluntier in the campagne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12049014</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12049014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53117</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 823:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short relation of the most remarkable transactions in several parts of Europe between the Christians and Turks including an exact diary of the siege of Buda / written originally by a person of honour, a voluntier in the compagne, and done into English by P.R.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour, a voluntier in the campagne.</author>
                  <author>P. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Randolph Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Mehmed IV, 1648-1687.</term>
               <term>Buda (Hungary) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53117:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT RELATION Of the moſt Remarkable TRANSACTIONS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF EUROPE BETWEEN THE Chriſtians and Turks; INCLUDING An Exact DIARY of the SIEGE of BUDA.</p>
            <p>Written Originally by a <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> a <hi>Voluntier</hi> in the <hi>Campagne,</hi> and done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>P. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Randolph Taylor</hi> near Stationers-Hall, 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53117:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53117:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT RELATION Of the moſt Remarkable TRANSACTIONS In ſeveral Parts of EUROPE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is no queſtion to be made but that the happy ſucceſs of the D. of <hi>Lorain</hi> ſince he undertook the command of the Imperial Forces, has won him the renown of being one of the greateſt Captains of his time. Nor was the raiſing the Seige of <hi>Vienna,</hi> aſſail'd with the whole Power of the Turkiſh Empire, the leaſt of his glorious Enterprizes, where the Preſence of the warlike King of <hi>Poland</hi> did no way eclipſe his Honour, while his Councils, his Conduct, and his Valour entitul'd him to an equal ſhare of the Victory with any of the Confederates. For that he then ſtood firm upon the Baſis of his own merit and courage, fortified with a long experience in War, is apparent by his ſingle Actions in the proſecution of that memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble overthrow.</p>
            <p>His chiefeſt buſineſs, during the ſeverity of ſo hard a Winter was to enlarge his Quarters into the Enemies Country which he did as far as <hi>Newſol</hi> upon the River <hi>Grana,</hi> by which means he kept <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanſel</hi> ſo cloſely block't up, that all the attempts of the <hi>Turk</hi> to relieve it were in vain. In the mean time he labour'd at Court the reinforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Army againſt the next Spring; and the accompliſhment of the League between the Emperour, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and which upon the 29th. of <hi>February</hi> was ſign'd by the Cardinal <hi>Bonviſi,</hi> in behalf of the Pope, by the Count of <hi>Conlinſeck</hi> and the Baron <hi>Straetman</hi> for the Emperour and Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> and for the Commonwealth of <hi>Venice</hi> by their reſpective Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, being to continue for fix years. Nor was he leſs careful in his endeavours to reduce the head of the Rebels, Count <hi>Teckelie</hi> by fair means, to which purpoſe a general Act of Oblivion was publiſh'd by the Emperour with pardon to all that would return to their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; which <hi>Teckelie</hi> himſelf was free to lay hold of, as a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53117:3"/>of <hi>Hungary,</hi> provided he did not expect to be conſider'd in any higher Degree. And indeed ſuch was the conſequences of that famous Enterprize wherein his Proweſs was ſo lately and ſo highly eminent that it ſeem'd to influence the more Northern people, and warm their valour in that extremity of weather, to add to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of his Triumphs.</p>
            <p>For about the midſt of <hi>January</hi> came News to the Court at <hi>Lintz,</hi> that the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> under the Command of their chief Leader <hi>Kuneſki,</hi> having ſtraighten'd <hi>Caminiac</hi> a ſtrong Garriſon of the <hi>Turks</hi> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> under the Leading of their own Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, joining in a Body of forty thouſand Men, reſolv'd to remove the Enemy at a farther diſtance from the Town. Of which the <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks</hi> having intelligence, drew together no leſs then thirty thouſand compleat, and with a ſpeedy march, unlook'd for, upon the fourth of <hi>December</hi> ſo furiouſly aſſail'd the Enemy, that they ſlew near Thirty Thouſand upon the place; and in the purſuit, the Earth being cover'd with the bodies of the ſlain for ſeveral Miles together, the two Chieftains of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> endeavouring to rally their men were both ſlain, at what time <hi>Haley Bey</hi> who commanded the <hi>Turks,</hi> being taken Priſoner, offer'd a Hundred Thouſand Crowns for his Ranſom, but the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> quarrelling about the diviſion of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſlew him in the heat of the Conteſt. With the <hi>Tartar</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals was alſo ſlain the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Biatogrod,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Mirza</hi>'s, who are the cheif Officers of quality among the <hi>Tartars.</hi> In purſuit of which Victory, the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> fail'd not to enter <hi>Budziack,</hi> where they waſted all before 'em with Fire and Sword not ſparing either Age or Sex.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Coſſacks</hi> ſo call'd from <hi>Coſack,</hi> ſignifying a Goat; becauſe they wandred like Goats upon the Mountains, or from <hi>Cazack</hi> in the <hi>Tartar</hi> Language, which ſignifies a Robber, were a ſort of Rovers, the ſame with the <hi>Banditi</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> firſt taken into pay by <hi>Stephen</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who gave them alſo leave to chooſe themſelves a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whom they pleas'd, of their own gang, to be conſirm'd by the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Prince, he aſſign'd 'em likewiſe the Caſtle of <hi>Techtimirocco</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the Banks of the <hi>Boryſthenes</hi> or the <hi>Nicper,</hi> with the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories belonging to it, for their habitation. And thus embodied into a kind of a Nation, they liv'd in ſubjection to the <hi>Polander,</hi> till the Reign of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus;</hi> but in the year 1638, they began to grow tumultuous and rebellious, from whence aroſe a moſt cruel War, wherein the <hi>Turks</hi> generally took their part, and at length by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Articles of Peace between the <hi>Ottoman</hi> and the <hi>Polander,</hi> concluded <hi>October</hi> 18th. 1672 all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> ſo call'd from the <hi>Tartar.</hi> word, which ſignifies a <hi>Border</hi> or <hi>Limit,</hi> as being the utmoſt limit of the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Dominions was ſurrender'd to the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> to hold of themſelves; the <hi>Polander</hi> at the ſame time, renouncing all his Claim, Right, Title or Pretenſion to it.</p>
            <p>In this Province ſtands the City of <hi>Camenecia</hi> or <hi>Caminiac,</hi> one of Natures wonders, as being ſeated upon a high and ſteep Rock, taken by the <hi>Turk</hi> in the year 1672 and now in a fair way to be retaken again.</p>
            <p>This Victory obtain'd in <hi>December,</hi> was ſeconded by another in <hi>January,</hi> at what time the new <hi>Palatine</hi> or <hi>Hoſpodar</hi> of <hi>Walachia Dukas,</hi> marching with 30000 men to diſplace <hi>Petrozenſco,</hi> whom the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53117:3"/>King of <hi>Poland</hi> had re-eſtabliſh'd in that Government, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have ſurpriz'd the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> in his march, was himſelf routed and taken Priſoner with his ſon, after he had loſt ſeventeen thouſand of his men upon the place, and two pieces of Canon.</p>
            <p>Some skirmiſhes and diſputes there alſo happen'd between the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts and the Rebels under Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> which though they were not ſo remarkable as the preceding, yet the Imperialiſts ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing they ſerv'd to enlarge their own and ſtraiten the Quarters of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>But ſo ſoon as the Seaſon permitted the Duke himſelf haſten'd to take the Field with all the Expedition he could, and ſo toward the beginning of <hi>June</hi> the Army being randevouz'd about <hi>Neſtria,</hi> he paſs'd the <hi>Danow</hi> at <hi>Komorrah,</hi> and march'd for <hi>Gran</hi> where he encamp'd, expecting the Regiments of <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia;</hi> and thence intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> upon the fourteenth of <hi>June</hi> he paſs'd the River again at the ſame place. Which he had no ſooner done, but upon the ſixteenth of <hi>June,</hi> he inveſted <hi>Vicegrade</hi> ſeated on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the River, and heretofore conſiderable for the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Reſidence of the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with a Body of Horſe, and the ſame evening attack'd and gain'd the Town; upon which the <hi>Turks,</hi> that were in the Caſtle to the number of ſeven hundred and forty men, came to a Capitulation the next day and march'd out with their Arms and Baggage. But while the Duke was thus employ'd, the Garriſons of <hi>Alba Regalis, Zygeth</hi> and other places, having notice that the Imperialiſts had left their Baggage at <hi>Gran,</hi> guarded only by a ſmall party of Horſe and Foot, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Major General <hi>Holloweil</hi> with a Body of ſix thouſand men advanc'd to <hi>Gran,</hi> and with ſo much fury fell upon the Imperialiſts that the foremoſt Troops being put into ſome diſorder, the Major General was after a brave reſiſtance ſlain. But then the Regiments of <hi>Rabata</hi> ſtanding the whole brunt of the Enemy, till the other Troops recovering out of their diſorder came into their aſſiſtance, they put the <hi>Turk</hi> to an abſolute flight, and purſu'd 'em for ſeveral Miles. In this encounter the <hi>Turks</hi> loſt 6 or 700 men, and four ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards, afterwards preſented to the Emperour; the Imperialiſts about two hundred; among whom the Baron <hi>Levi</hi> was ſaid to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kill'd or taken. Count <hi>Rabata</hi> was alſo a Priſoner, and tied by the <hi>Turks</hi> to one of their Horſes tayls, but releas'd in the purſuit.</p>
            <p>All this while <hi>Newhauſel</hi> had been cloſely block'd up by <hi>Caprara,</hi> who had kept it all the winter time from being reliev'd by the <hi>Turks;</hi> ſo that it was by this reduc'd to pinching extremity: And therefore the <hi>Ottomans</hi> finding they could do no good with ſmall parties, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to ſuccour the Town with a compleat Army of 20000 men. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having intelligence that the Enemy was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd as far as <hi>Vaccia,</hi> between <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Novograde,</hi> reſolv'd to give 'em battel. To this purpoſe he ſet forward, and coming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſight of the Enemy, found 'em drawn up in <hi>Battalia</hi> upon the Hills near <hi>Vaccia,</hi> having on the right Wing the River <hi>Danow</hi> and a large Moraſs, and the left ſecur'd by a thick Wood. Thereupon the Duke having embattell'd his own men, about eleven a Clock at Noon mov'd directly toward the Enemy in two lines, beſides the reſerve, and the Troops left to guard the Baggage. The <hi>Turks</hi> ſuffer'd him to advance without oppoſition till he came to the foot of the Hill,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53117:4"/>and then with their uſual cries made a deſperate charge upon <hi>Taff</hi>'s Regiment, which was almoſt in the middle of the line, and where the Duke being in perſon, had his own Horſe wounded under him, and two more Horſes of the Officers next him kill'd with Piſtol ſhot. The <hi>Turks</hi> having thus ſpent their firſt fury, and obſerving the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Imperial Battalions, turn'd their back for a while; but then rallying again, fell upon the Chriſtians on every ſide, and then wheeling off, return'd a third time and made another deſperate charge, but not being able to break their Enemies array, who ſtill made their way in good order, they fell into confuſion, and routed by their own fears, the Horſe abandoning the Foot, betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to flight; being purſu'd by the Imperial Cavalry of the firſt Line for above an hour: but by reaſon of the ſwiftneſs of their Horſes they ſoon got out of ſight. The Foot thus left to mercy were moſt of them ſlain; the reſt eſcaping into <hi>Vaccia.</hi> This Body conſiſted of about 20000 men, of which four thouſand were <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> commanded by the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s under him. The <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> himſelf was ſuppos'd to be ſlain, his Horſe being tak'n by a private Soldier of <hi>Taff</hi>'s Regiment, who preſented it to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> Nor did <hi>Vaccia</hi> protect the fugitives, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts ſoon after making themſelves Maſters of the Town, where the <hi>Turks</hi> ſurrender'd at diſcretion. So that in all the number of the Enemy ſlain was reputed to be 3000. and 1500 taken Priſoners, and among the reſt a <hi>Baſſa</hi> and ten <hi>Aga</hi>'s; with ſeven pieces of Canon and ſeveral Colours. As for the loſs of the Chriſtians it was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, as not having miſt above twenty or thirty men in the whole Action; <hi>Vaccia</hi> being thus ſurrender'd, <hi>Novograde</hi> was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately quitted by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and aſſoon poſſeſs'd by the Imperialiſts.</p>
            <p>This Battle was fought the 27th. of <hi>June,</hi> which Month thus end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this memorable defeat of the <hi>Turks,</hi> at the beginning of <hi>July,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> haſten'd with his victorious Army to <hi>Peſt,</hi> another Garriſon of the <hi>Turks</hi> on the farther ſide of the <hi>Danow,</hi> and began without delay to batter the Town with his Canon and Fire Bombes. But the <hi>Turks</hi> in great fear and diſorder retir'd with the beſt of their goods to <hi>Buda,</hi> having firſt ſet fire to ſeveral houſes in the Town, as alſo to the Bridge, to prevent the purſuit of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts. But they entring immediately, ſoon became Maſters of the Fire, and of a place, which had the Enemy had the courage to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, might have coſt both time and men.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being thus in poſſeſſion of <hi>Peſt</hi> plac'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a conſiderable Garriſon conſiſting of two Battalions of Foot, and a party of Dragoons; and being reinforc'd by <hi>Caprara</hi> with a body of ſix thouſand men, among which were ſix hundred <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> that had deſerted Count <hi>Teckelie;</hi> and by <hi>Lubomirskie,</hi> with an addition of 4000 <hi>Poles,</hi> in all 40000 ſtrong, repaſs'd the <hi>Danow</hi> upon the 11th. and 12th. of <hi>July,</hi> over a Bridge of Boats laid over the River not far from the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew;</hi> while <hi>Leſley</hi> was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with the Forces under his command toward the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> to make good that paſs.</p>
            <p>Upon the 14th. of <hi>July</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having forc'd the <hi>Turks</hi> from the Poſts which they had on this ſide <hi>Buda,</hi> came with all his Forces and ſate down before the Town.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buda,</hi> by the <hi>Germans</hi> call'd <hi>Ofen,</hi> is a City of the lower or hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53117:4"/>
               <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſtanding for the moſt part upon a Hill near the Banks of the <hi>Danow,</hi> the other part lying in a plain level about fifty four <hi>German</hi> Miles from <hi>Vienna</hi> to the South, and forty nine from <hi>Belgrade</hi> to the North. Formerly the Reſidence of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Princes, and which King <hi>Sigeſmund</hi> adorn'd, with ſeveral Magnificent Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; particularly with a Palace built after the old Roman man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, environing the Caſtle with beautiful Walls and Terraſs'd Walks, that overlookt moſt pleaſant Gardens and Fields adjoyning. It is fortified with ſtrong Walls and Bulwarks, containing a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber both of private and publick Structures exquiſitely built, ſo that all the reſt of <hi>Hungary</hi> can hardly be ſaid to ſhew anything more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant, more pleaſant, or more ſecur'd by art and nature: It was taken the 12th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the year 1519. after it had been eleven times aſſaulted by the whole force of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being ſate down before this City, in a ſhort time made himſelf Maſter of the lower Town and lodg'd his Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Ditch under the Wall of the upper Town, before he ſent his firſt expreſs to the Emperour.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Duke lay in this poſture before <hi>Buda,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> in a Body of thirty or five and thirty thouſand men hover'd about two <hi>German</hi> miles from the Town near <hi>Hanſchabets,</hi> expecting all oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to relieve it.</p>
            <p>But the Duke not willing to be peſter'd with ſo troubleſome a neighbour and the toyl of continual skirmiſhes, reſolv'd to diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the main Body from whence theſe petty Obſtacles of his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Enterpriſes had life and Motion. To this purpoſe about the 21 or 22 of <hi>July,</hi> after he had left all his Infantry and what Horſe was neceſſary to continue the Siege, with the reſt of the Cavalry and a thouſand Foot commanded by the Count of <hi>Averſperagh,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with fifteen hundred <hi>Huſſars</hi> under the conduct of Count <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterhaſi,</hi> Governour of <hi>Raab,</hi> he march'd all night to encounter the main Body of the Enemy, who though very well entrench'd, ſo ſoon as they ſaw the Imperialiſts, came out of their Camp about twenty thouſand ſtrong: The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> divided his Army into two Battalias; the two Wings being each compos'd of thirty Squadrons of <hi>Cuiraſſiers,</hi> and ten of Dragoons, and the Foot being plac'd in ten ſmall Bodies between the intervals of the Horſe. The <hi>Turks</hi> had plac'd 2 or 3000 <hi>Janizaries</hi> upon the deſcent of the Hill, and ſix thouſand Horſe at the foot of the Hill toward the right Wing of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, where were poſted a thouſand <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral movements, which plainly demonſtrated their deſign of attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Adverſaries in the Flanks, which while the other labour'd to prevent, the fight began, wherein the <hi>Turks</hi> maintain'd a ſharp diſpute for the time; and making uſe of policy as well as ſtrength drove a hundred Camels upon the left Wing of the Chriſtians, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have put it into diſorder, but the ſtratagem failing, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of 30 Dragoons which turn'd 'em quite another way, the <hi>Turks</hi> recoyl'd, and were follow'd ſo cloſe, that at length being all in confuſion, they betook themſelves fairly to their Heels, and fled up to the top of the Hill, where they routed their own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, while the Victors in the purſuit became Maſters of their whole Camp, as at the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> their Tents, their Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage conſiſting of 1000 Camels and 500 Mules, their Artillery being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53117:5"/>eight peices of Canon and all their wealth. Four thouſand were ſlain upon the place, among which were a thouſand <hi>Janizaries,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what were kill'd and wounded in the purſuit by the <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who was order'd to continue the chaſe. The great Standard of <hi>Mahomet</hi> was taken, which the <hi>Sultan</hi> uſually gives to the grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> when he takes upon him the general command of the Army, and the Pavillion of the Turkiſh Officer, who is known by the Title of <hi>Seraſquier;</hi> and was chief Commander of the Army in the abſence of the <hi>Viſier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſame time Count <hi>Leſly,</hi> lying before <hi>Berzeche,</hi> or <hi>Virovitza</hi> a Town about two Miles diſtant from the <hi>Dravus,</hi> had intelligence given him that the <hi>Turks</hi> were drawing together all the force they could make between the <hi>Savus</hi> and the <hi>Dravus</hi> to ſuccour the place. More particularly that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Marotz,</hi> who had the guard of the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> was advanc'd with two thouſand five hundred <hi>Turks</hi> as far as <hi>Flatina</hi> in order to his joyning with the <hi>Beg</hi> of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neg</hi> and Governour of <hi>Gradiſchia,</hi> who for that purpoſe were upon their march with 1400 men more, thereupon he ſent away four thouſand <hi>Croats</hi> under the Command of Count <hi>Trautmanſdorffe</hi> to hinder the Enemies conjunction; who marching all night about ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the next morning ſet upon the <hi>Baſſa</hi> in his Camp near <hi>Flatina;</hi> where after a ſhort reſiſtance the <hi>Turks</hi> were forc'd from their Poſt, with the loſt of many men kill'd and taken Priſoners; the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſu'd as far <hi>Tarbina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then the Victors returning from the purſuit, met with a party Commanded by the <hi>Beg</hi> of <hi>Zarney,</hi> who knew nothing of the defeat of the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Marotz,</hi> with whom they were going to joyn, and by that means unluckily dropt into the mouth of a victorious Enemy. For the Chriſtians fleſh'd with their late ſucceſs, fell upon the half ſurpriz'd Infidels with that vigorous Reſolution, that they ſlew near five hundred upon the place, took many more Pris'ners with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable quantity of Ammunition and Proviſion intended for the Releif of the Garriſon. So that the loſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> in both theſe Actions was reckon'd to be no leſs than a 1000 of the choiceſt men of theſe two Bodies ſlain out-right, while <hi>Trautmanſdorffe</hi> thus dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Crown'd with freſh Lawrels return'd with Plunder and Pris'ners to the <hi>Leaguer</hi> before <hi>Vicovitza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day being the twentieth of <hi>July</hi> Count <hi>Leſley</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Priſoners that had been taken, to be plac'd at the head of his Trenches, and among all the reſt he order'd one to acquaint the beſieged with the defeat of the Body from whence they expected their Relief; to which although the Garriſon return'd no Anſwer; yet did the General grant 'em till five in the Evening to conſider of certain Propoſitions for the ſurrender of the Place: and for two hours there was a Ceſſation from all Acts of Hoſtillity.</p>
            <p>But then the ſame Evening the Beſieged began to fire again: Thereupon the General gave order for the filling up of the Mote and the Moraſs, and for the providing ten Thouſand Faggots for that purpoſe. Which being done and all things now ready for an aſſault; the Beſieged began to reflect upon the danger they were in, and unwilling to venture the laſt extremity, in ſeaſon deſir'd a Parley, and preſently after the Hoſtages were exchang'd, though the Articles were not agreed upon till the next day. But then all things being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53117:5"/>concluded, <hi>Virovitza</hi> was ſurrenderd to <hi>Leſley,</hi> and ſix Hundred Men with the like number of Women and Children march'd out of the Town, leaving behind 'em ſixteen Peices of Cannon, having all upon 'em the Arms of the Emperours <hi>Maximillian</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Garriſon according to the Articles of Capitulation was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd two Miles from the City by a Guard of the Beſiegers; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards meeting with a Party of <hi>Croats,</hi> they were all or the moſt part ſtripp'd, plunder'd, and cut in peices together with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children.</p>
            <p>Upon the taking of <hi>Virovitza,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> having abandon'd <hi>Soppia, Fatina,</hi> and <hi>Werazin,</hi> Count <hi>Leſley</hi> ſate down before <hi>Bezowits,</hi> which not being able to hold out made a timely Capitulation, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd upon the ſame Articles that <hi>Virovitza</hi> had done. By which means he had both leiſure and opportunity to lay a Bridge over the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> that ſo he might be in a condition to joyn the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> upon all occaſions.</p>
            <p>While thus Count <hi>Leſley</hi> ſecur'd the main <hi>Leaguer</hi> at a diſtance the Imperialiſts took their ſeveral Poſts about <hi>Buda;</hi> and though the lower Town had no other defence then a ſingle Wall, yet did the General think it convenient to make formal Approaches to it, as well becauſe of the great Garriſon that was in it, as becauſe of the Communication which they had with the upper Town.</p>
            <p>Theſe Approaches therefore being finiſh'd, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> caus'd an Aſſault to be made upon the lower Town upon the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>July,</hi> wherein the Imperialiſts behav'd themſelves with that Bravery that they made themſelves Maſters of the Place, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great number of <hi>Janizaries</hi> that defended it; of whom there were ſlain not fewer then a Thouſand who had not time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the upper Town.</p>
            <p>The next day the Duke caus'd an attack to be made upon the Fort of St. <hi>Gerard,</hi> which the Enemy quitted together, with the Cannon that was in it. And now being thus Maſter of the lower Town and the Fort, he caus'd his men to take two Poſts more; one next the great Tower in the way to <hi>Gran,</hi> the other near the Court in that joyn'd the Town and the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the Beſieged were not idle, but finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very much annoy'd by the Chriſtians from St. <hi>Gerrards</hi> Hill, upon the firſt of <hi>August,</hi> made a thund'ring Salley, toward the cloſe of the Evening, which began a ſharp and fierce encounter between them and the Chriſtians; in which the beſieged ſuffer'd a repulſe; wherein the ſlaughter of the Enemy could not chooſe but be very conſiderable as being repell'd, when it coſt the lives of two hundred of the victorious Beſiegers; among whom the Signior <hi>Cavallieri</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel of the Regiment of <hi>Grana</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>Bagni</hi> were ſlain; the Count of <hi>Sherfenberg,</hi> Major General, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Parella,</hi> with ſeveral other Officers wounded.</p>
            <p>The day following the Enemy made another Salley, but retir'd preſently again; perceiving perhaps thoſe diſadvantages in the day; on which they had run headlong the night before in the dark.</p>
            <p>Whatever were the reaſon of their ſudden retreat, certain it is, that the <hi>Turks</hi> got nothing by either Salley, but broken pates; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Chriſtians gain'd a work which the Beſiegers had caſt up, to guard a breach which the Beſiegers had made in the Wall of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53117:6"/>Town; and for ſome days continu'd their Batteries with their <hi>Bombs</hi> and <hi>Cannon</hi> with ſo much vigour, that they made ſeveral other breaches, and proceeded ſo ſuccesfully in their Mines, that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> minding to give a general aſſault, ſent an Officer with two Turkiſh Priſoners before-hand, to ſummon the Governour <hi>Cara Mahomet</hi> to ſurrender the Town; and to let him know that if he ſuffer'd things to run to the laſt extremity, he muſt not expect any Quarter: Which was anſwer'd with no leſs inhumanity then haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs by the <hi>Barbarian:</hi> For after he had caus'd the heads of forty Chriſtian ſlaves to be cut off in his own and the preſence of the Meſſenger, he bid him tell his General he would neither give nor expect Quarter.</p>
            <p>However he did not long enjoy the ſatisfaction of his cruelties, nor his inſulting replies. For upon the ſifth of <hi>August</hi> the haughty <hi>Turk</hi> receiv'd his death wound by a ſhot from the Camp as he was viewing one of the Chriſtian Batteries; of which he died within two or three days after. He was ſaid to be one of the beſt Officers the <hi>Turks</hi> had; as being one who had ſerv'd in the Sieges of <hi>Candia, Caminiec,</hi> and <hi>Vienna,</hi> in the battle of <hi>Choczin</hi> againſt the <hi>Poles,</hi> and in all the moſt memorable Occaſions of his time. To whom im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſucceeded <hi>Cheitan Baſſa,</hi> no leſs infortunate, as being kill'd with a Cannon ſhot before he was hardly warm in his Government; ſo that the cloſeſt <hi>Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> to prevent a <hi>vacuum</hi> in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, was forc'd to take upon him the defence of the place.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Chriſtians, tho' continually vex'd with warm and frequent Alarums and Salleys, fail'd not to make their approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with a moſt obſtinate reſolution. To which purpoſe upon the eighth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Chriſtians after they had beaten back a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the <hi>Turks</hi> who Salli'd out early in the morning, with ſome loſs to themſelves, but a greater ſlaughter of the Enemy. They alſo ſprung a mine the ſame day in a place near one of the principal Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries of the Beſieged; which tho' it took not the intended effect, yet were the Beſiegers thereby nothing diſcourag'd in their laborious Progreſs, but having finiſht the reſt of their Mines within ſome few days after ſprung 'em together, which ſo well ſucceeded that they made a very large Breach in the Wall. However the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> did not think it fit to give a general Aſſault; for that he found the beſieged had made a large retrenchment behind the Wall of the Town, and underſtood moreover, that the Garriſon was very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous.</p>
            <p>But there was a more powerful reaſon for the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to defer a general Aſſault, which was his ſmall number of Infantry reduc'd by continual Salleys and hard labour to little more then 8000 fighting men; and thoſe diſhearten'd by the loſs of ſeveral of the young <hi>German</hi> Nobility, and their inſpiring Leaders. And therefore he thought it more proper to ſtay for the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours that were daily expected.</p>
            <p>While they therefore are marching to his relief, it may not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs to give a brief accompt of what happen'd in other parts in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Diverſions which the Chriſtians made in other places; which no queſtion were no ſmall hindrance to the relief of the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Buda.</hi> Among which we are not to imagine that of the <hi>Venetians</hi> to be the leaſt. Who with their own and ſeveral Galleys of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53117:6"/>
               <hi>Malta,</hi> the Pope and Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> conſiſting in all of forty ſix Galleys, ſix Galleaſſes, thirty three Men of War, and ſeveral other ſmaller Veſſels man'd with twenty four thouſand foot, and four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred mounted Cavalry, under the Command of <hi>Moroſini,</hi> as Captain General, put forth to Sea about the nineteenth of <hi>July</hi> from <hi>Corfit,</hi> and the next day arrived before <hi>Sancta Maura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Sancta Maura</hi> is an Iſland joyning almoſt to the Continent, ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Golf</hi> of <hi>Larta,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Preveſa,</hi> famous for the victory of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> againſt <hi>Marc Antony;</hi> and wreſted from the <hi>Venetians</hi> by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> the ſecond; ſince which time it has continu'd under the ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the great annoyance of the <hi>Venetians</hi> by Pyracie; being well peopled and about ſeventy Miles in Circuit. The main For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs is ſeated at the mouth of the Gulf, on a little neck of Land, very ſtrong and well fortified, having the Sea on the one ſide and a great Moraſs on the other.</p>
            <p>On the 21th. of <hi>July</hi> the light Veſſels enter'd the Port of <hi>Damata,</hi> on the right ſide of the Iſland, ſufficiently capacious to receive a large Fleet, and ſecur'd by a Mole. Signior <hi>Monetta</hi> landed firſt with a hundred and fifty men; and after him General <hi>Straſoldo</hi> with two Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian Regiments, the Popes and the Infantry of <hi>Malta;</hi> at what time the reſt of the <hi>Venetian</hi> forces and thoſe of the Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Weſt ſide.</p>
            <p>The next day the General ſent a Summons to thoſe in the Fort to ſurrender it: To which the Governour return'd for anſwer, That the Fortreſs belong'd to the Grand Signior, who had given him charge of it, and that according to his duty he would defend it to the laſt.</p>
            <p>Thereupon a party of Horſe was ſent toward the Suburbs of the Town on the Eaſt ſide which they found quitted by the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The 23th. of <hi>July</hi> the Ships began their batteries from the Sea, but with ſmall ſucceſs by reaſon of the high Winds.</p>
            <p>The next day the whole Fleet was ſo diſpos'd, as to do more ſignal execution with their Canon; and ſome of the Galeaſſes roaring within Musket ſhot, threw a great many Bombs and Fire-balls into the Place, which did great execution, yet not ſo but that the <hi>Galleas</hi> commanded by General <hi>Carnaro</hi> receiv'd two dangerous ſhot from the enemies Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, the General himſelf being wounded with a ſplinter; beſides that the Galley belonging to Signior <hi>Quirini,</hi> which row'd the Galleaſs, was very much diſabl'd.</p>
            <p>The 25th. a Battery was finiſh'd of 10 peices of Cannon carrying Balls of fifty pound weight, and upon the 27th. another ſomewhat nearer the Caſtle, both on the Eaſt ſide of it.</p>
            <p>The day following the Chriſtians poſted themſelves in the Suburbs and rais'd another battery on the Weſt ſide.</p>
            <p>Two days after a large breach was made in the Wall; at what time the <hi>Turks</hi> Sally'd out, but being diſcover'd were ſoon beaten back. Thus diſappointed, they labour'd to fill up the breaches with bags of Straw and packs of Wool; but that labour being eaſily fruſtrated by the Cannon from the batteries, the Chriſtians advanc'd their Trenches to the Counterſcarp, and made a deſcent into the Mote.</p>
            <p>After that upon the fourth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> they made two deſcents more into the Mote, their Cannons having made another wide breach and diſmounted all the Cannon of the Fort on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſixth all things being prepar'd for a vigorous aſſault; the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53117:7"/>General ſent a ſecond Summons to let the beſieged underſtand, That if they refus'd the ſecond offer of his Clemency, they were to expect but the utmoſt ſeverity. Thereupon, the next morning three Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were ſent out, who being brought before the General, caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the ground and deſir'd they might be admitted to compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Which being granted, the Conditions were ſoon accepted, that the Garriſon ſhould march away with their Arms and what they could carry about 'em: and the Chriſtians took poſſeſſion of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs: wherein they found fourſcore Peices of Braſs Cannon, of which twenty had the Arms of St. <hi>Mark</hi> upon 'em, together with a great quantity of Ammunition and Proviſion.</p>
            <p>There march'd out of the Garriſon about 600 men and the like number of women and Children who were convey'd to <hi>Preveſa;</hi> and by this means a great many Chriſtian ſlaves were releas'd.</p>
            <p>During the whole time of the Seige, which laſted about ſeventeen days, the Chriſtians loſt 400 Men, the <hi>Turks</hi> 300.</p>
            <p>While things thus proſperouſly ſucceed at <hi>Sancta Maura,</hi> the Seige of <hi>Buda</hi> carri'd on with ſo much vigour, and the noiſe of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Forces, ready to joyn with the Beſiegers, ſo Alarums <hi>Adrianople,</hi> that the <hi>Siraſquier Baſſa</hi> receives poſitive orders to relieve the Town or die in the Attempt. But General <hi>Leſly</hi> lay ſo unluckily poſted in his way, that he deem'd it neceſſary to remove ſo formidable an Enemy, before he could proceed any farther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leſley,</hi> having receiv'd advice of this, and that to accompliſh his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he was decamp'd from <hi>Walpa</hi> re-inforc'd with ſeveral Bridges of Horſe and Foot from <hi>Boſnia</hi> and other places with a reſolution to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack him, poſted himſelf in an advantageous place, between two Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſes, about half an hours march from the Bridge which he had made over the <hi>Drave,</hi> at which time there came to his aid a ſeaſonable recruit of 800 <hi>Croatian</hi> Gentlemen, and a 1000 Soldiers from the Province of <hi>Zethmar,</hi> which he plac'd before the two Moraſſes that cover'd the wings of his Army.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had he ſecur'd himſelf, but the Enemy appear'd in ſight upon the nineteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and the next day made a furious on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet upon the <hi>Croats</hi> and <hi>Zethmarians,</hi> thinking to force them from their Station. But they ſo rudely entertain'd their Aſſailants, and were ſo bravely aſſiſted by the Dragoons and Musketeers that were ſent to their relief, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were forc'd to retreat with conſiderable loſs, Nevertheleſs ſoon after they return'd again with a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and renewed the encounter with ſuch a redoubl'd reſolution, that the <hi>Croats</hi> were conſtrain'd to give ground, leaving three Standards in the victors hands: which ſo highly enrag'd the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> that he came on with his main Forces and fell upon two of <hi>Leſley</hi>'s Poſts on that ſide of the Moraſs where the German Cavalry and Infantry were plac'd; who ſo ſtoutly behav'd themſelves, that after an obſtinate conflict for three hours together, the <hi>Turks</hi> were forc'd to retire, notwithſtanding the inequality of their number: For that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> had no leſs then thirty thouſand in his Army, <hi>Leſley</hi> not above fourteen thouſand to encounter him.</p>
            <p>In this Action the <hi>Baſſa</hi> loſt five hundred of his beſt men; of the Chriſtians about two hundred were kill'd and wounded.</p>
            <p>All this while great were the expectations on both ſides at <hi>Buda;</hi> while the beſieged look'd many a long look for the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53117:7"/>beſiegers impatiently attended the <hi>Baverian</hi> re-inforcement. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it might have been worſe for the Chriſtians had not their cauſe born up their reſolution above their expectations. For about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>September</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> himſelf, wearied with the toils of Wars, and watchful cares of an induſtrious General, fell ſick of a Fever which held him till paſt the middle of the Month, ſo that he was forc'd to retire for a while to a place near the Camp call'd the old Town. At the ſame time alſo, ſickneſs forc'd the Duke of <hi>Croy,</hi> and Commiſſary General <hi>Breiner</hi> to leave the Camp. Which diſtempers of the General, and other great Officers though they had no fatal effect upon the Army, yet it caus'd ſome abatement of their wanted ſucceſſes. 'Tis true that the Enemy was repuls'd with loſs in two Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys which they made, the firſt upon the eighth of <hi>September</hi> to their great damage, and a ſecond the ſame Evening with as ill ſucceſs; for the Battalions of <hi>Souches, Beck</hi> and <hi>Newburgh</hi> coming into the timely aſſiſtance of thoſe that guarded the Trenches, the ſlaughter of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy happen'd to be very great; however they loſt Lieutenant Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Souches</hi> with ſeveral other officers and forty Soldiers. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for want of Foot, the beſieged ruin'd the Works which the beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had rais'd to cut off the communication between the Town and the River.</p>
            <p>Before this alſo upon the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> made a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Salley in the night, which before they had not done, the fury of which fell upon the Dragoons who did not expect their coming, of whom they ſlew a hundred and fifty with little loſs on their ſide.</p>
            <p>The next morning likewiſe they made a ſecond Salley with Horſe and Foot, but the beſiegers having timely notice of it, repell'd the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy with a far greater ſlaughter, and ſeveral Priſoners taken.</p>
            <p>Equal or rather far better ſucceſs had Collonel <hi>Heuſter</hi> who being ſent out with a thouſand Imperial <hi>Cuiraſſiers,</hi> and ſix hundred <hi>Hungarian</hi> Horſe, and underſtanding that a great Convoy, conſiſting of four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Wagons laden with Proviſion, drawn every one by four Oxen under the guard of four thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> had paſs'd the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and were marching for <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> plac'd a convenient Ambuſcade in their way, which at the firſt diſcharge kill'd above fifty of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and put the reſt to flight: Yet were they not ſo totally routed, but that they ralli'd again in hopes to recover the Waggons which they had ſo cowardly abandon'd and fell upon his rear. But it was then too late, for they that were ſcar'd before not being able to endure a ſecond charge were ſoon conſtrain'd to ſhift for their lives, while <hi>Heuſter</hi> return'd to the Leaguer with all his booty, which prov'd a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſupply for the Army.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the moſt remarkable paſſages that happen'd before the Conjunction of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Forces: which about the middle of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> was happily notifi'd to moſt parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> for upon the twenty eighth of <hi>August</hi> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Vienna</hi> by water, where he was firſt complemented by the Deputies of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian</hi> Nobility, and then met by the Emperour himſelf, who carry'd him in his Coach to the Palace, being ſaluted all the way by a treble diſcharge of all the great Guns of the City.</p>
            <p>On the third of <hi>September</hi> he departed from <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the next day arriv'd at <hi>Presburgh</hi> with his Infantry and train of Artillery.</p>
            <p>The 5th. he parted from thence for <hi>Gran,</hi> where after he had ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouz'd all his Horſe and Foot he march'd in a body to <hi>Buda,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53117:8"/>arriv'd there about the 9 or 10th, of the ſame Month. On which day was obſerv'd at <hi>Vienna</hi> the Anniverſary of the Cities deliverance by the victorious Arms of the Emperour, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes of the Empire. There was a general Proceſſion of all the Clergy as well Secular as Regular; at which the Emperour aſſiſted on Foot with the Nobility, and the Officers of all the Soveraign Courts in their Robes; which being once over, all the Guns about the Town were thrice diſcharg'd.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Elector arriv'd at the <hi>Leaguer</hi> with all his Forces, the Imperial Army upon a Muſter appear'd to be 20000 Horſe and 10000 Foot, beſides the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Succours, which were about ſixteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and the recruits daily expected from <hi>Suabia</hi> and <hi>Bohemiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> as if the recruit of his Army had recruited his health, purſu'd the chaſe of victory with his accuſtom'd vigor. His Soldiers alſo laboured in their approaches with renew'd courage, while the <hi>Bavarians</hi> undertook that part of the Town that lay next the water, from whence they ſoon depriv'd the beſieged of enjoying their late Conveniencies. For now upon a general Muſter, the whole Army appear'd to conſiſt of twenty thouſand Horſe, and about ſix and twenty thouſand Foot, reckoning in the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſuccours which together with the recruits expected out of <hi>Suabia</hi> and other Parts were deem'd ſufficient to fight the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> and maintain the Seige at the ſame time. For now the intelligence grew hotter then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> had receiv'd poſitive orders to raiſe the Seige at the hazard of his life.</p>
            <p>Of this <hi>Leſley</hi> gave ſpeedy notice both to the Emperour at <hi>Vienna</hi> and to the Camp before <hi>Buda.</hi> Who keeping his Poſt at the Bridge of <hi>Turanowath,</hi> with a reinforcement of three thouſand <hi>Croatians,</hi> could not be forc'd from his Moraſſes, but ſtill watch'd the motion of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> therefore reſolv'd to leave him, and march di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly for the relief of the diſtreſs'd Town. However he could not decamp ſo ſecretly, but that the Country People gave <hi>Leſley</hi> intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of his march; who tho he thought it not convenient to ſtir from his Poſt, yet ſent a Party after him, and finding that he was upon his march toward the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> diſpatch'd away his Adjutant General <hi>Miglio</hi> to give notice of his deſign. But notwithſtanding the ſeverity of his receiv'd orders, and that he was advanc'd ſome part of his way, when he underſtood that the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſuccours were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, and that the convoy ſent to <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> was ſurpriz'd and taken by the Imperialiſts, he put a ſtop to his march, and as it was reported, was reſolv'd to have repaſs'd the Bridg of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> as one that diſpair'd to accompliſh the relief of the Town. And it is thought he would have made no farther attempt, had not freſh Commands and repeated Menacies conſtrain'd him to proceed.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Bavarians</hi> briskly carried on their two new at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks toward the <hi>Water-gate,</hi> which they were inform'd by a Gunner taken Pris'ner ſince the War, and eſcap'd a little before was the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſide of the Town, and where in a ſhort time they had compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three Batteries, while the Imperialiſts with no leſs induſtry carry'd on the other attaques, in order to a general Aſſault. And ſo great were their hopes to carry the Town by ſtorm, that upon the 22d. of <hi>September,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> ſent a Corporal with a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pris'ner into the Town with Letters to the <hi>Baſſa</hi> in Command, to let him know that his Highneſs gave him an Accompt of his arrival before the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53117:8"/>Town, from whence he was reſolv'd not to ſtir till he had reduc'd the place under the obedience of the Emperour; and withal admoniſhing him not to let things come to extremity. But ſuch was the reſolution of the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> that after he had aſſembl'd the Principal Officers of the Garriſon, he ſent for the Corporal, and when he had read the Letters in their hearing, addreſſing himſelf to the Chriſtian Officers, made anſwer, That he thank'd his Highneſs for the Accompt he gave him; that he had beheld the Arrival of his Forces; and that he underſtood very well the Rules and extremities of War, as having been a Souldier for many years; however that he wou'd not ſurrender the place ſo long as he had men and Ammunition to defend it, and proviſions to ſubſiſt: Which ſaid, he gave the Corporal twelve Ducats and ſent him back to the Elector.</p>
            <p>But as this was no more then was expected, ſo both <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Bavarians</hi> omitted nothing either of Art or Induſtry to carry on their approaches, wherein the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were ſo ſucceſsful, that with a mine which they ſprung they made a conſiderable breach in the Wall, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the frequent Sallies of the <hi>Turks</hi> and the great number of Granado's and Artificial Fires which they flung into the Trenches of the Chriſtians; which did very little or no harm, in regard that the beſiegers ſecur'd themſelves with Gabions and packs of Wool.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus the one ſide laboured in aſſurance of being ſpeedy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the place, and the other as ſtoutly defended the Town in hopes of releif, the Imperial Camp was warmly alarum'd with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the <hi>Seraſquier;</hi> who was ſaid to be advanc'd with a Body of five and twenty Thouſand Horſe without Cannon or Infantry as far as <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> formerly the place of the Coronation and enterment of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Kings, two and forty Miles diſtant from <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> leaving the <hi>Elector</hi> to manage the Seige, ſet forward upon the 16th. of <hi>September</hi> with a Body of twenty Thouſand Horſe and Dragoons to meet and fight him by the way. But when both ſides came in view of each other, the Duke found the <hi>Baſſa</hi> ſo ſtrongly entrench'd with the River <hi>Sarwitz</hi> before him that he did not think fit to attaque him at ſo much diſadvantage. The wary <hi>Turk</hi> alſo kept cloſe within his Trenches, unwilling to hazard a battel ſo far from the Place which he was to releive. So that after a ſhort ſtay the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> thought it more convenient to return to the Seige, leaving the Prince of <hi>Baden</hi> with ten thouſand Horſe to obſerve the Enemies motion; upon his return to the <hi>Leaguer,</hi> a Council of War was call'd where it was reſolv'd by the <hi>Imperialists</hi> to expect the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in their Camp; to which purpoſe the Elector and Duke attended by all the General Officers viſited all the Quarters and Lines of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation, as well as the Trenches and Poſts toward the Town, and every where gave neceſſary Orders.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> obſerving the retreat of the Duke came boldly on, and upon the 22th. of <hi>September,</hi> attack'd the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Camp with great fury in two places, endeavouring to break in upon the Imperialiſts and to force his way to the Town; but he met with ſo ſtout and undaunted a reſiſtance, that after a ſharp and obſtinate fight for ſeveral hours, wherein many were ſlain on both ſides he was forc'd to retire in much diſorder, and to leave two of his Standards behind him. In the mean time, the beſieged made a deſperate Salley with fifteen Hundred men as well Horſe as Foot, and fell upon the Guards of the Trenches with ſo much reſolution, that the Beſiegers were forc'd to give ground; upon which the encourag'd <hi>Turks</hi> advanc'd,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53117:9"/>ruin'd ſeveral of the Beſiegers Works, and one of their principal Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, nailing the Cannon that was mounted upon it, with the loſs of three hundred of the Chriſtians: but then certain Squadrons of Horſe ſpeeding to their aſſiſtance, the <hi>Turks</hi> were again beaten back to the very Gates of the Town, with the ſlaughter of above two Hundred men.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> alſo retreated that Night about two Miles from the <hi>Leaguer;</hi> but the next morning he made another attempt, though not with that Vigour as the day before; and ſeem'd by the event to be more out of deſign then that he thought to do any good. For while the Imperialiſts were engag'd, five Hundred <hi>Janizaries</hi> wading through a Moraſs, which was lookt upon to be impaſſable up to the Arms in Water and Mud, got into the Town; yet not with that good luck but that they left ſome of their Company ſticking in the Mire, who became the Sport of the Musketeers.</p>
            <p>Theſe two attacks ſeconded by a Salley, and three brave Repulſes coſt the lives of many valiant Men. However the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> hoping he had done enough to ſave his Neck by putting five hundred men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town, was glad he was got off ſo, making all the haſt he could from his unwelcome entertainment, being purſu'd by the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> till he had ſecur'd himſelf under the Guns of <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>September</hi> drew toward an end; a Month no leſs remarkable for other notable atcheivements perform'd againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> to their conſiderable dammage, which as they very much weaken'd the <hi>Ottoman</hi> force, ſo they greatly impeded the Releif of <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For on the one ſide the <hi>Morlakes</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> toward the beginning of this Month, made an incurſion into the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Territories, not far from <hi>Cliſſa,</hi> and after they had burnt ſeveral Villages, brought away a conſiderable number of Priſoners. In their return they met with eight Hundred <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe marching toward <hi>Cliſſa,</hi> which they utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, killing two Hundred upon the Place, and taking all their Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage. Nor was this all; for being reinforc'd with a recruit of ſix Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, they poſted themſelves near <hi>Cliſſa</hi> in order to their Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with General <hi>Mocenigo,</hi> who was reſolv'd to attack that place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a neat City with a ſtrong fortified Caſtle.</p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time another Party of <hi>Morlakes</hi> and <hi>Heydukes,</hi> being joyn'd with the <hi>Banditi</hi> ſent by the Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> to ſerve the <hi>Venctian</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> defeated another conſiderable Body of <hi>Turks</hi> that were drawn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the vicinity of <hi>Spatetro</hi> to hinder their incurſions, ſlew between two and three hundred upon the Place, took ſeveral Pris'ners, and brought away a conſiderable Booty of ſeven hundred Head of Cattle.</p>
            <p>At a farther diſtance, the King of <hi>Poland</hi> toward the latter end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> inveſted the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Jaſlowits,</hi> not far from <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and ſummon'd the Governour to ſurrender, who at firſt according to the haughty manner of the <hi>Turks,</hi> return'd q fierce anſwer. That he had Powder and Bullet ſufficient to defend the Place, and would therefore maintain it to the laſt extremity; but no ſooner did the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Batteries begin to play, and the Bombs and Careſſes to fly about his Ears, but ſuddain Terrour ſeiz'd the beſieged in ſuch a manner, that they deſir'd a Parley, which ſoon ended in a Compoſition; in purſuance of which, the <hi>Turks</hi> march'd out the third day after the Seige, to the number of 500 fighting men: at what time ſeveral of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Officers beſought the King for his Protection, and that they might have liberty to remain within the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Territories, being unwilling to return home for fear of being queſtion'd at their return for their Cowardice.</p>
            <p>Which ſucceſs was attended by another of no leſs importance; for much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time, the Treaſurer of the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> wreſted a compleat Victory from the <hi>Waywod</hi> of <hi>Walachia,</hi> to the deſtruction not only of his own For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Auxiliaries that were joyn'd with him, who together with their lives loſt alſo their Camp and all their Baggage. Succeſſes ſo much the more conſiderable, becauſe they kept the <hi>Turks</hi> upon their Guard in thoſe Parts from whence the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> expected his chiefeſt Reinforcements.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53117:9"/>
            <p>In the Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> General <hi>Schultz,</hi> who commanded the Emperour's Forces in thoſe Parts, having notice that Count <hi>Tekeley</hi> had put an 150 Men with two Peices of Canon into <hi>Zeben,</hi> a ſmall Place bordering upon the Mountains not far from <hi>Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> haſten'd thither, took the Place, and put all the Garriſon to the Sword, in revenge of what <hi>Tekeley</hi> had done before, upon his taking a ſmall Garriſon from the Imperialiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zeben</hi> thus recover'd, General <hi>Schultz</hi> ſent ſeveral ſpies into Count <hi>Tekeley</hi>'s Army; by whom being duly inform'd of the number of his Men, and the Situation of his Camp he reſolv'd to give him a viſit. Accordingly, leaving the lumber of his Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage at <hi>Zeben,</hi> upon the ſeventeenth of <hi>September</hi> about five in the Evening he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd with all his Cavalry and part of his Infantry, which the Horſemen carry'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind 'em. About three in the morning, being come near the Enemies Camp, he put his Men into Order, and fell ſo ſuddainly upon the Rebells, that they had no time to put themſelves into a Poſture of defence. All they could do in ſo great a confuſion was to think how to ſave themſelves; ſo that ſome flying one way; ſome another, the Imperialiſts were ſoon Maſters of the Enemies Camp, all their Artillery, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of five Peices of Cannon; all their Ammunition, Tents and Baggage, even to the very Coach and Standard of <hi>Tekeley.</hi> He himſelf was in his Bed, and having hardly time to put on his Cloaths, fled away with only two or three perſons in his Company. In his Tent were found his Sable, his Papers, his wearing Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, his Plate and Money.</p>
            <p>It is certainly reported that above four thouſand were ſlain or drown'd in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Tarza</hi> and <hi>Secſo,</hi> which they endeavour'd to paſs in their flight, being cloſely purſu'd all the way by the Imperial Cavalry. Fourteen Standards and other Colors were afterwards ſent and preſented to the Emperour as the Trophies of this Victory.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of his good Fortune, the Victorious General upon the 24th. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> ſate down before <hi>Barfeodt,</hi> a Town well fortified with a ſtrong Wall with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Towres and Redoubts, and a deep Mote, wherein was alſo a Garriſon conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of between three or four Hundred men, beſides Inhabitants that bore Arms. Who having notice of the General's March, made all the Preparation they could for a ſtout reſiſtance, uncovering their Houſes to prevent their being fir'd by the Bombs and Fire-Works of the Aſſailants, removing their Goods into Vaults and Cellars: and then caſting up ſeveral Works within the Town.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the General had poſted his men, he caus'd a large Battery to be rais'd, under the ſhelter of which five or ſix Hundred choſen men commanded by Collonel <hi>Veterani</hi> advanc'd to the Mote and making a deſcent, lodg'd themſelves with their Ladders under the Wall. Which ſo diſmay'd the Inhabitants, that they preſently diſpatch'd out Commiſſioners to capitulate; who being ſent back for the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of their demands, <hi>Veterani</hi> in the interim made the Inhabitants ſenſible how he was Poſted under the Wall, and withal told 'em that he had prepar'd ſuch a Mine, which would not only blow up the Wall but a good part of the Town. Which ſo terrifyed the credulous <hi>Hungarians,</hi> that they quickly condeſcended to meaner Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, deſiring only the preſervation of their Ancient Priviledges, as well in Civil as Eccleſiaſtical Matters. The Soldiers were to March out with only their Arms; and what they could carry about 'em, with liberty to ſuch as would, to be entertain'd in the Emperours Service. Which Conditions being agreed to, the Garriſon march'd out, and General <hi>Schultz</hi> took poſſeſſion of the Town.</p>
            <p>From hence he march'd to the Caſtle of <hi>Muſcowitz,</hi> which he immediately Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd; but the Governour relying upon the ſtrength of the Place, and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Garriſon conſiſting of 400 Men, beſides a great many Martial Peaſants, inſtead of returning an Anſwer, hung out a red Flag. Upon which the General forthwith began to raiſe his Batteries and make his Approaches, at the ſame time throwing into the Town a great number of Granado's and Bombs; by which means in a ſhort time he made a deſcent into the Mote. So that the Garriſon apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the danger of a ſtorm from thoſe that proceeded with ſuch a ſwift and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Reſolution, after a Seige of fix days ſurrendred upon Condition.</p>
            <p>During this Seige, Captain <hi>Molner</hi> one of <hi>Schultz</hi>'s Officers meeting with a Party of 300 Rebells, under the Command of <hi>Subeida,</hi> Count <hi>Teckeley</hi>'s great favourite, who were going to put themſelves into the Caſtle of <hi>Maſkowitz,</hi> totally routed their whole Body, took <hi>Subeida</hi> and his Wife Priſoners; and beſides other good Booty forty Thouſand Crowns in ready Money.</p>
            <p>Nor was the <hi>Venetian</hi> Fleet leſs active in the <hi>Archipelago;</hi> For on the ſeventeenth, of <hi>September</hi> they made a deſcent near to <hi>Dragomaſto,</hi> anciently a City of <hi>Acarnania</hi> call'd <hi>Oeniade,</hi> ſeated at the mouth of the River <hi>Achelous;</hi> ſo famous among the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53117:10"/>of the <hi>Pozes.</hi> Where they were no ſooner landed but they were joyn'd by two Thouſand and five Hundred of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> deſirous of their ancient Liberty; and thus embody'd march'd 50 Miles up into the Country, waſted the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Acurnania,</hi> burnt two great Towns, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ragoſi,</hi> and <hi>Zapaachi,</hi> together with a great many ſmall Villages; defeated the <hi>Sangiac</hi> of the Province, who endeavour'd, with what Forces he could get together, to make oppoſition againſt 'em, and at length, with a great Booty and many Pris'ners, return'd to their Fleet.</p>
            <p>But now to return again to the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> the ſucceſs of which <hi>Leaguer</hi> all <hi>Europe</hi> liſten'd after with attentive Ears, we find the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> after an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to relieve the Town, twice repuls'd toward the beginning of <hi>October;</hi> and then when he found himſelf diſappointed, retiring back again in haſty diſorder with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and twenty Thouſand Horſe at his heels, not daring to make head, or look back till he had poſted himſelf under the Cannon of <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the Elector no leſs eager in the purſuit of Honour toil'd in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring all things ready for a general Aſſault, raiſing Batteries, advancing his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and opening Mines, in a mon ent to demoliſh the labour of many years. While the perverſe and half ſtarv'd Enemy, as if they had only fed upon the hopes of Releif, as reſtleſly labour'd with continual Salleys to diſturb the Progreſs of his indefatigable Endeavours. This was the Pains and Travel of this Month which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd both Parties.</p>
            <p>Upon the Second of <hi>November</hi> they made a Salley with three Hundred Men, but were beaten back again by the <hi>Bavarians</hi> with the loſs of ſeventy of their Number, who were ſlain upon the Place.</p>
            <p>The next day they appear'd again with between three and four Hundred Horſe: but perceiving that the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were drawn up in a Poſture ready to receive 'em, they preſently retreated back.</p>
            <p>The very ſame day they made another Salley on that ſide next to old <hi>Buda,</hi> where the <hi>German</hi>'s guarded the Trenches; but there they were ſo warmly welcom'd, that they were glad to retreat in great diſorder leaving twelve of their number Pris'ners, beſides what were ſlain in the skirmiſh. Theſe Pris'ners, upon their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, affirm'd that the <hi>Janizaries</hi> who got into the Town a little before, brought no Proviſions along with 'em; of which however there was then at that time ſo great want, that a pound of Horſe-Fleſh was ſold for nine Pence.</p>
            <p>On the Fourth of <hi>November</hi> the <hi>Bavarians</hi> ſtorm'd the Tower of the Caſtle which looks toward the Water, by others call'd the Great Tower; but were not able to make themſelves Maſters of it, though they contended for it ſeveral hours together with great ſlaughter on both ſides: However afterwards, they made a ſhift with a Battery of ſix Peices of Cannon to beat down all the Towers of the Caſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Turks</hi> Ears, and to lodge themſelves very near the Caſtle it ſelf: ſo that now all the publick Intelligence in this Part of the World ſounded loud to a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſault, and the fatal Determination of ſo long and ſo bloody a diſpute.</p>
            <p>And there is no queſtion to be made, but that never any Beſiegers labour'd with more indefatigable pains; with ſuch an obſtinacy, that neither inundation of Water; nor unſeaſonable Weather could ſtop the Career of their Travel, beyond all the <hi>Roman</hi> Induſtry before <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> But when the day was appointed, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> relaps'd to ſuch a degree that the <hi>Margrave</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> was ſent to Command the Army during his Indiſpoſition; and more than that, not to mention the Rainy weather alleadg'd for another Cauſe, the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> ſaid to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> ſo ſoon as the Duke had ceas'd his purſuit, advances again and lodges himſelf within four <hi>Hungarian</hi> Miles of <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It behov'd him to uſe all his Wits to ſave his Neck: and therefore while he lay there, he provided five Boats laden with Proviſion and Ammunition to be ſent up the River, and at the ſame time having given orders to the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Agria</hi> to Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum the Imperialiſts of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st,</hi> reſolv'd himſelf to advance near the <hi>Leaguer;</hi> as if he intended to aſſail the Chriſtian Camp, to the end that by the favour of the Night and ſuch a Diverſion the ſupply might the more eaſily be got into the Town. But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> having notice of his deſign, commanded Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Dunevelt</hi> to paſs the <hi>Danaw</hi> with a Body of Horſe near <hi>Vacia,</hi> which he did, directing his March toward <hi>Peſt:</hi> So ſoon as the <hi>Turks</hi> perceiv'd the Imperial Troops, they retreated with all the haſte they could. On the other ſide <hi>Dunevelt</hi> advancing along by the River ſide, had the good Fortune to meet with five Boats; which he took with eaſe, and put to the Sword all the <hi>Turks</hi> that were in 'em. By which means the ſupport intended for the Garriſon became a ſupply no leſs ſeaſonable to the Beſiegers.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53117:10"/>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this Diſappointment, and that the Beſieged were ſaid to be reduc'd to four Thouſand Men; they forgot not their wonted Cuſtome of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Sallies; firſt upon the thirteenth of <hi>November,</hi> at what time they were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in again with little loſs to the <hi>Beſiegers:</hi> The next day they came forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and forc'd the <hi>Bavarians</hi> from their Works, but other Forces coming in to their timely aſſiſtance the Chriſtians regain'd their Poſts, though with the loſs of two Hundred Men. The fifteenth day they made another Salley with ſix Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men, and prevail'd ſo far, that they took away and carry'd into the Town the very Deal Boards which the Beſiegers made uſe of in working their Mines: Which nevertheleſs was not ſo prejudicial as their Counter-mines which now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to take Effect.</p>
            <p>And certainly it was encouragement ſufficient for the Beſieged to do their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to preſerve themſelves and annoy their Enemies; when they ſaw the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> with his numerous Troops o'r-ſpreading all the neighbouring Feilds; and watching all opportunities to ſend 'em freſh Relief: For the <hi>Baſſa</hi> was all this while poſted within five Miles of the Town; ſo that the Imperial Cavalry being hinder'd from forraging ſuffer'd very much; while the Beſiegers ſeem'd in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner beſieg'd themſelves.</p>
            <p>But that which mainly incommoded the Chriſtians was the unſeaſonable Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which had not only drown'd ſeveral of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Trenches, but begot ſundry diſtempers as well among the Officers as Soldiers, lying wet and cold, which had much impair'd the Infantry, and much weaken'd the Cavalry; inſomuch that the Regiments of <hi>Savoy, Magni,</hi> and <hi>Heuſter</hi> were reduc'd to Thirty and Forty Men.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all the hardſhips which they ſuffer'd, the Imperialiſts could not ſo ſoon reſolve to go without the purchaſe of a Place which had coſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of ſo much time and blood. And therefore perceiving that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> embolden'd with a Reinforcement of forty Thouſand freſh Men, and fourteen Peices of Cannon, drew nearer and nearer, within two Miles of the Camp, a Council was call'd, wherein they reſolv'd to abide the Enemy in their Trenches which were deep and well fortifi'd.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the wary <hi>Turk</hi> did not think it convenient to make a general Attacque upon the Enemies Camp, where he well knew he ſhould meet with a dangerous oppoſition. For upon his firſt approaches certain Detachments of the Imperialiſts being ſent out to encounter his formoſt Troops; had given 'em ſuch proofs of their Courage, that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> was forc'd to retire: Which the Beſieged impatient of his delays obſerving, and to ruine one of the Chriſtian Batteries which did very much annoy the Town, made a deſperate Salley upon the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but were repuls'd with conſiderable loſs; at what time Collonel <hi>Kreig</hi> who commanded in the Trenches, two Captains and a Lieutenant of the ſame Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were ſlain.</p>
            <p>On the 25th. the Beſieged made another Salley wherein they ruin'd ſeveral of the Beſiegers Works and diſcover'd their chief Mine. Nor was it poſſible to prevent ſome ſucceſſes of the Enemy, where ſo numerous an Army daily hover'd ſo near their Camp. Among the reſt it was not the leaſt, that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Agria,</hi> having forc'd the Entrenchments which the Imperialiſts had made on that ſide next to <hi>Peſt,</hi> and put to the Sword thoſe few men that were left to guard 'em, had convey'd about eight Boats with Men and Proviſions into the Town; that another ſtrong Party of the <hi>Turks</hi> being ſent out towards old <hi>Buda,</hi> had ſurpris'd ſeveral of the Imperial Forragers, had taken 500 Horſes and all the Baggage of the Count <hi>de Schram;</hi> and that the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were forc'd to abandon their Mines, being all fill'd with water.</p>
            <p>On the 27th. of <hi>October</hi> the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> advanv'd ſo near the Chriſtian Camp that he beat in their main Guard. But the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Horſe commanded by Prince <hi>Lubo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirski</hi> not only gave a ſtop to their further Progreſs, but conſtrain'd 'em to retire with ſome loſs. Nevertheleſs the Beſieged encourag'd with their new recruits of Men and Proviſion the ſame day made ſo deſperate a Salley with 2000 Men, that they forc'd the Imperialiſts from their Trenches, and being conducted by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado who two days before had got into the Town, to their Principal Mine, they took the Powder out of it, ruin'd all their Works on that ſide and advanc'd to the Beſiegers chief Battery; but the Forces that guarded the next Poſt, haſt'ning to their Releif; the Enemy was beaten into the Town again.</p>
            <p>Thereupon at length in conſideration of the Seaſon, the ill Condition of the Army, and for that their Principal Mines and Works were ſpoil'd, both Generals reſolv'd, in purſuance of the Emperours Orders, to raiſe the Seige. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all the ſick and wounded men, to the number of 8000 being firſt ſent away
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53117:11"/>with the Baggage and Camp Attendance, the great Guns were drawn off from the Batteries; and, for the defence of the Army in their retreat, planted in the Iſland of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> where the whole Army; conſiſting of about 30000 men paſs'd the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw,</hi> the firſt of <hi>November</hi> over a Bridge of Boats; the Cavalry facing the Enemy while the Foot march'd off. Which was perform'd with that warineſs and exact Order; that they were neither attaqu'd by the <hi>Seraſquier;</hi> nor from the Town; ſo that they loſt not ſo much as one map in the Retreat.</p>
            <p>This was the unfortunate Iſſue of this Summers Seige of <hi>Buda,</hi> which might have well deſerv'd the Pen of another <hi>Homer</hi> to eternize the performances of thoſe great Perſonages; no leſs famous then his <hi>Achilles</hi>'s or <hi>Patroclus</hi>'s, whoſe valour how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever could not prevent their being buried in their own Trenches. They fought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the honor of one part of <hi>Greece,</hi> theſe for the Good of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſtrenuouſly endeavouring to have recover'd by their courage what had been wreſted from the Chriſtians formerly; and all the while every Salley and Repulſe of the Enemy was a Theme for Heroick Invention: As for thoſe that ſurviv'd, they continu'd their indefatigable endeavours to level the Fortifications, not only of Art but ev'n Nature it ſelf, till Nature releiv'd Nature with the Stoppings and Inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Seaſon; and Winter prov'd no leſs favourable to the <hi>Turks,</hi> than the Summer had been to the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Yet is not this the firſt Seige of this Nature rais'd after the loſs of men, and the laborious toyls of the Beſiegers fruſtrated. We read of the famous City of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> that when the Walls were almoſt levell'd with the Earth, and the yawning Breaches gap'd to let in the numerous Enemy, the whole Force of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire daily reinforc'd, continually recruited, was forc'd to retire with ſhame and diſhonour from the Ruins of their own Batteries.</p>
            <p>But much more Freſh in memory is the late Seige of <hi>Vienna</hi> it ſelf, a much weaker Town then <hi>Buda,</hi> aſſail'd and ſtorm'd on every ſide for ſeveral Months, and yet the haughty <hi>Baſſa</hi> that inveſted it, was at length conſtrain'd not to riſe end march fairly off, but to fly from his Leaguer and leave the whole Plunder of his Camp to the Victor. It was not ſo here; for tho' the Beſiegers were inferior in number to thoſe that came to the releif of the Beſieged, yet they maintain'd their Poſts, drew off all their Artillery, ſent away all their wounded and ſick People, all their Baggage, fac'd the Enemy and march'd off leiſurely without diſturbance or the loſs ſo much as of one man.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore true that the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves may have ſome reaſon to be glad; nor are they to be blam'd for being glad to find themſelves in ſome meaſure repaid for their greater and much more ignominious loſs before <hi>Vienna,</hi> by releiving ſo ſeaſonably a Town which has preſerv'd 'em the cheifeſt Trophy of all their former <hi>Hungarian</hi> Conqueſts. But that there ſhould be a ſort of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Chriſtians, that ſhewed themſelves ſo penſive as they did, when the Town was near loſing, and now ſhare with the <hi>Turks</hi> in the Mirth of their Triumph, cannot otherwiſe be thought than very ſtrange. It is ſaid of <hi>Solyman,</hi> who firſt took <hi>Buda</hi> from the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that with tears in his Eyes he bewail'd the ſlaughter which his Sword had made, and the untimely end to which he had reduc'd the unfortunate <hi>Lodowic</hi> the Second; but theſe people are ſorry that the Chriſtians were not all Buried under the Walls of <hi>Buda</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Turk</hi> could not do it in performance, pleaſe themſelves with purſuing and deſtroying the retreating Beſiegers in their diſcourſe and reports. But then again when we conſider that all this is for Count <hi>Tekelie</hi>'s ſake, upon whom they look as the great Champion of <hi>Hungarian</hi> Liberty and Property, and Freedom of Conſcience, as they call it, 'tis not ſo much to be admir'd that their Intereſts are ſo twiſted with his, and that their ſimpathy extends ſo many <hi>German</hi> Miles to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole or congratulate the loſſes or ſucceſſes of the <hi>Turk</hi> his Protector. But this it is, not to underſtand the depth of true Proteſtant Intereſt; otherwiſe what greater wonder in the world then that <hi>Julius,</hi> the Head of the Papiſts, ſhould be condemn'd for calling in the <hi>Turks</hi> to his aſſiſtance; when it ſhall be lawful at the ſame time for theſe ſublimated Proteſtants to repine at the ſucceſſes of their follow Chriſtians, and rejoice at the proſperity of Infidels? But the <hi>Turks</hi> were ſo kind as to relieve the diſtreſſed Pope beſieg'd in <hi>Bologna,</hi> and now have rais'd the drooping Spirits of theſe Proteſtant Muſſel-men by the relief of <hi>Buda.</hi> 'Twas pity Count <hi>Tekelie,</hi> their ador'd friend, was ſo ſhamefully ſurpriz'd that their joy might have been compleat. However we have ſtill this advantage over 'em, that they are glad the Seige is rais'd; and we are much more glad, 'twas rais'd without the loſs of Men or Reputation. Which the <hi>Turks</hi> could not ſay, when chas'd and ſcattet'd from <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
